[Music]
hey welcome to day four of the coding
camp I'm here with the the family again
today so we got keegan age eight
we've got mom and Bowen Bowen is age six
and then we've got sissy age ten you
guys ready to code some today mm-hmm all
right let's show a example of what we're
gonna be making today so we're gonna be
making a race car game today so here's
my race car he's going around the track
what we're gonna do is we're gonna draw
this car so we're gonna actually draw
the sprite ourselves the car is gonna
always be moving and I'm using the right
arrow to turn right and then the left
arrow to turn left and as you can
imagine the car is going around the
track at whatever speed you the programmer
design and if you touch the color
green which is around the outside and in the
middle then my car crashes and so it
crashed and it actually is playing a
little animation as well I really like
this project cause it's got a lot of
good enhancements here's an enhanced
version of one I made this is a
two-player game so like one person would
be the blue car and then the other
person would be the red car and they
would play against each other and you
can also do things like if you touch
these little red pills they speed you up
if you touch a green pill I'm sorry
green speeds you up and then red slows
you down there's all kinds of things you
could do you could even add things like
a finish line he would get there and win
but instead he's gonna crash
and so I like the different enhancements
and things you can make to this one so
let's go ahead and get started actually
building it some of the learning
objectives this time that are new is
we're going to be learning about
animations and functions so some really
important things today
so go and click on create new project
and like I always do I like to like on
blank block coding project so there's a
lot of different things that have to get
done we've got to draw the track we've
got to draw the car we've got to add the
code for the car can't really decide
where I want to start because there's so
much to do let's start with a little
drawing right so let's start with
drawing our car so we don't need the
monster he's a great actor but we don't
we don't need him
this time instead we're gonna add our
own actor we're gonna draw a car so I'm
gonna say add actor and I'm gonna say
drawing tool now everybody draws at
different speeds so what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna kind of like quickly make mine
and then encourage you to pause the
video when you make yours so here's what
I'm gonna do the first thing I like to
do is I like to make sure I'm zoomed to
see the whole canvas my daughter
McKinley yelled at me just like why
don't you ever use the 75% button it's
right here in the middle and I said
because I didn't know about it thank you
for teaching me about it
so if you click in the middle you can
pick a zoom and 75% is it good zoom
for at least mine so what you want to do
is you want to decide what color you
want your car to be so I've been using
red as my car so I just kind of pick out
a red and like I said I'm gonna do this
kind of quick but what I like to do to make
a car is I like to draw a block which is
roughly in the middle and that's going
to be my car and then I draw a rectangle
kind of for the windows and so I'm gonna
go ahead and draw another rectangle here
because I had to click off that rectangle
a rectangle for the windows this is just
my style for my car if you want your car
to be entirely different that's fine and
then I want to draw that same color
again so I'm gonna use the eyedropper to
pick it back and then draw kind of like
another rectangle here and that may not
feel like a car at first it kind of is
gonna work out to be a car and so what
I'm gonna do is I'm going to draw some
lines to connect from the corners here
to the corners there and I think that
I'm starting to kind of have the feel of
the top view of a car so you want the
top view of a car a car is not a car
until you have tires that's what I'm
gonna do is I'm gonna make my tires and
whenever I make something I still select
it that's an opportunity to hit ctrl-c
ctrl-v and you can make another one of
them so if you want to you can kind of like
copy paste your tires again I know that
this is way too fast for you to directly
follow along but I'm trying to kind of
show you the the basics and then once
you've got your four tires on I consider
that good enough right if you want to
make enhancements to it like you want to
add headlights or you want to add taillights
that's fine but I think that this is a
perfectly acceptable car so now I'm
gonna name my costume right now it's
called blank I'm gonna name it car and
I'm gonna go and hit save just so that I
can save my current car and now what I
want to do is I want to make another
so pause the video until you make
your car alright pause the video make
your car alright now we've all got a car
so now I want to make another version of
the car that's crashed right so a crash
car so to make another version of
something right now it's selected up
here I'm gonna click on this copy button
right so when I click on copy it makes a
copy of my car
this next car I'm gonna call crash now
there's a bunch of ways to crash a car
you could just scribble on it with lines
that's certainly a fine way to to crash
a car you know so you could just kind of
scribble all over it
you can make you know orange flames on
top of it oops I thought I was gonna
change colors there orange flames on
it and that's kind of crashing as well
there's another trick that I find fun
this selection tool you can kind of like
select a wedge of your car and then just
kind of like move it or rotate it and I
find that that's always a really good
way to kind of like make something have
an appearance of you know you just got
crashed right so and if you wanted to go
crazy I know that every time I teach
this class
somebody just completely explodes their
car there's nothing wrong with that
right it personally I think it looks
better if it's kind of close to a car
still but you do whatever makes you
happy so there's my crash car so pause
the video until you have these two
animations by the way you can hit the play
button here and it'll just kind of show
you like here's normal here's crashed so
when you hit a wall you're gonna switch
to that crash alright so I'm gonna save
that up and I'm gonna head back to my
game now my car is currently much too
big for a track right so I'm gonna have
to make my car much smaller and again
this is why I encourage you not to
necessarily go nuts with drawing
headlights and stuff because once your
car is small enough you can only see so
many of those details
while we're still in the drawing mood
we've still got to draw a track so let's go
ahead and draw a track really quick so
click on the stage say add background
click on the paintbrush because we're
gonna draw our track and say draw an
image now your track let me get this 75%
thanks to McKinley your track is gonna
need to have a border around the outside
so people can't just like drive off into
space and it's gonna have something in
the middle and it's going to have enough
room that you can actually get around
but other than that you can do whatever
you want so what I'm going to choose to
do is I'm going to make a border around
the outside that's maybe like 10 pixels
in thickness I'm gonna choose a like
maybe a green color of some sort
maybe I'll choose like a dark green by the way
this hex value is gonna be
useful later but I'll just wait until
later before I worry about that to
make a border around the outside I like
to draw it to be nearly big enough maybe
I'll make it perfectly big enough if you
make it perfect then great you're done
if it's not quite perfect you just have
to grab these little handles and just
scooch it all the way till there's
nothing showing on the outside this is
the same thing that we did for the maze
so hopefully it's something you're
familiar with now we need to draw
something in the middle the middle can
be whatever you'd like if you wanted to
kind of be rectangular you can do that
if you would rather it kind of be oval
based you know you can do that but it
should be a track that people can you
know get around right so maybe I'll make
them kind of go through there and then
up through here but they should be able
to drive around it your car is only so
big so you might want to give yourself
some some space to kind of drive things
around right maybe I'll add another
little hump here if you'd like to keep
the background white that's fine but if
you'd like to use a fill and make it
kind of like a gray color that's also
fine whatever you prefer
also feel free to decorate I always
like to put my name on things right so
this
is dr. Fisher's track we'll go with the more
formal dr. Fischer right it always
likes to drop down a little bit at the
end though oh well I'll consider that a
feature this time and I think that that
looks looks good enough for me
so pause it as you need and make sure that
you've got some type of track that you
can get around and then go ahead and hit
save all right so now we're ready to
start in with the code drawing
is definitely a useful skill I
definitely want you to do it but I think
we're good enough that you don't have to
watch me do it anymore you can just
start making them yourself
so now it's time for the code so here
you will have to kind of follow along
with me click on the car if it bothers
you the name of my car is
currently actor so I'm gonna rename him
race car Oh while I'm naming things I
should probably save my project I
usually forget to do this until like
way later but you really should save
early and save often right so I'm just
gonna call it race car track I don't
want to publish it yet I'll publish it
later I just wanted to go ahead and save
it early because I've done a lot of
drawing right and I don't want to lose
all my drawings but now I'm ready to add
some code to my race car so my race car
needs an on start we've done that many
times and in our projects that's
just as soon as you hit the start button
that's stuff that happens and we want
some things to happen forever so we're
gonna add a forever loop so go to
control and go ahead and grab a forever
loop and we want to do things like we
want to check to see if the user is
telling us to turn we want to move
forwards we want to check to see if
we're crashed and then of course we have
to add that that wait so that our loop
doesn't happen like too fast
now normally we just go grab the code
and just put it in here and there's
nothing wrong with that but today I want
to teach you something new about
functions click on the button that says
functions
today's game we're going to make using
functions functions are good for making
code that you can reuse it's also good
for organization so what is a function
let's go ahead and make one we'll learn
about it so click on create function
we're gonna make a function and here you
have to do some typing that says check
for turns with functions in tinker you
can use capital letters you can use
lowercase letters you can put spaces in
the name of the function doesn't matter
I'm going to make mine check for turns
and just use spaces as appropriate now a
function can also have parameters we're
not going to worry about that today
maybe tomorrow we'll do that with our
with our stars right but check for turns
and click on create now when you click
on create something happens and they
make for you a spot for this function
now usually it shows up right on my
screen and I can see it but if somehow
you don't see that just like zoom out
until you find it and then move it to
where you can see it but what's gonna
happen here is under this check for
turns I'm going to put some code and
then whenever I want to call that
function I'll have to call up from my
main loop let's go ahead and write the
function together and then we'll call it from
our main loop so check for turns a check
is an if statement so we know we're
gonna have to add some if statements to
this function we're gonna need a grand
total of two if statements so I'm going to
move over one if statement and I'm
building up this function right and then
I'm going to bring another if statement
also into my function now it currently says
if false then but really this is just a
placeholder so if some condition happens
then run this code the condition we're
looking for is the user pressing the
left arrow so let's go to sensing and
what we're looking for is we're looking
for are they pressing a key right so
really what we want to do is we want
like pressing some key and down here is
a good one key up arrow pressed now
that's the wrong key but you can see
that that's probably a good starting
point
and we don't want to check the up-arrow
we want to check the left arrow and then
for the other one we want to also check
a key and we're gonna do the right arrow
now I'm moving a little bit fast today I
don't know I guess it's just warm
outside but feel free to pause the video
if I'm doing things too too quickly
right so I've got a function over here
I'll make it so can see all my code I've got a
function over here with two if
statements in it and right now I'm
making this function first but I'm not
actually calling this function we're
gonna get to that in a second so this
function if you're touching the left
arrow we want to turn to the left some
number of degrees right so let's go
ahead and find motion and so if I'm
pressing left arrow I want to turn left
so you gotta kind of like look at the
little arrows on here and if I was a car
this bottom one is a left turn and then
this top one this top one is my right
turn great now the amount 15 degrees you
just have to kind of play with it and
see see how it goes it depends on how
fast your your timing is so I'm just
gonna leave it as 15 for now and if I
have to change it later I have to change
it later so now we've written a function
so if we ever want to use this code we
can call this function let's go ahead
and do that so go back to functions and
this check for turns function that we've
made we want to call it as the first
thing in our forever loop so the first
thing we do is we check for turns so now
the way our code works is it it hits
that function call it hops over to this
function and it runs it and then control
comes back over here now the next thing
I want to do after I check for turns is
I want to move the car forward so now
I've kind of like done my steering I
want to move it forwards that's in motion
I want to move 10 pixels
now after I move 10 pixels what I want
to do is I want to check for a crash and
then I want to have a short time delay
let's add the time delay and test it and
then we'll worry about crashes later so
let's add that time delay time delays
are over in control they're near the
bottom but not all the way to the bottom
and it says wait one second and I'm
going to pop that in there now one
second is a very long time that would
make your game feel very like jumpy so
we're going to use the the number that
we've used in the past and that's 0.05
that's one twentieth of a second it
makes your game play at 20 frames per
second essentially so let's try it if it
all works what should happen is you
should be able to steer your car around
using the left and right arrow now you
can decide for you what you want to do
about speeds so right now the speed is
that he's going forwards at 10 pixels
and he's turning at 15 degrees now
that's actually kind of a slow turn
sorry kind of a slow speed but kind of a
fast turn right if you like that leave
it right you don't you don't have to
change it if you want to tweak it a
little bit
feel free to tweak it so if you wanted
to say move at 15 you could if you
wanted to turn a little less hard you
could take those 15s down to tens and
you could see what that was like right
so now I don't turn as sharp but I move
kind of faster right so with your track
and your car decide what you want your
speeds to be and then just whatever you
decide you want it to be that's where
you leave it cool so I think it's
looking pretty good so let's go ahead
and add some more stuff I'm gonna click
save really quick so we use this
function purely for organization right
so it makes our main loop easier to read
so it says check for turns move 15 now
we want to check for crash
lets make another function so click on
functions create function and we'll call
this one check for crash again you could
actually name your function anything you
wanted upper case lower case using
spaces doesn't matter in Tynker just
pick a name that you like and you'll see
I can kind of see mine sticking out over
here you'll see that it adds a function
stub for you so make sure you find that
stub right because that's that's
important that's where we gonna put your
function now just to be different this
time let's go ahead and call the
function first and then we'll write the
function second so to call the function
you take this check for crash you can
kind of see how it's a different shape
I'm gonna choose to put it right between
the move and the time delay does it have
to go there not really it can go about
anywhere in the loop because it doesn't
matter what order you do these things
they come around so fast that it'll
check for the crash pretty often but I'm
gonna check right after I move now if
you were to play your game right now it
would not check for crashes all it would do
is it would call the function check for
crash which is empty and then carry on
with life right so functions aren't
magic just because you say hey call a
function that says check for crash it
doesn't just do it it does whatever code
you've got there so let's go ahead and
add some code inside check for crash so
in order to do this you need a pencil
and paper which I forgot again today so
I'm gonna pause the video and go get a
pencil and paper I'll be right back alright
I've got my pencil and paper magically
instantly and so what we need to do is
we're going to need to check if we're
touching the color of the track so I
know that I'm going to need that color
so I'm just going to go get it first so
to go get that color you can click on
the pencil icon for the stage because
there is this there is a costume there
you can just click on the pencil and we
need to figure out what color is my
track and simultaneously what color is
my outside wall
so this game is simple you click on the
eyedropper you click on your color you
click on the the multicolored tool and
then you say hex still cracks me up so
write down your color mine appears
to be that crazy combination of letters
and numbers again the letters are going
to be a through F so you don't have to
worry about like is that a zero is that
O (letter) it's a zero because it can't be now
alright so now we're gonna check for
crash checking for something is an if
statement so we're gonna say if so it's
in control that's the top one in control
so if this condition then run this code
the condition we want to check for is in
sensing we want to check if we're
touching a color and then this is where
you need to type in that number that you
wrote down these boxes are always kind
of annoying I find that if I click at
the end of it and I just backspace over
it oops alright so I'll type in my
number here and again you might have to
fight with this box some until you get it
use the left and right arrow keys to
kind of navigate back and forth and
delete key until you work it out now
you'll know that it works because it's
gonna match the color perfectly right so
at least you do get that confirmation
before you run your code that yeah it's
gonna work right all right so now if we
are touching that color what do we want
to have happen well we want to switch
our costume to that crash costume we
also want to decide like do we want to
just end the game outright or what do we
want to do for now we will just end
the game like after a short pause so
let's go ahead and switch costumes so
that's going to be in looks and we're
going to say switch costume switch to
costume and now if you named your
costumes they'll have good names I was
good I named mine car and crash so I'm
gonna say switch costume to crash now
whenever I start dealing
with costumes like this like if I switch
to crash later I find that it's always
good practice to switch to your normal
car right on the start up sometimes it
turns out not to be necessary but I
always welcome doing it so here's what
I'm gonna do I'm gonna grab another
switch to costume and I'm gonna put it
between on start and forever this is a
good place to do kind of like your set
up work right and so in this area we're
gonna switch to the car so that way
even if it's got crashed in a previous
round
it'll be reset now what we're actually
going to do is we're just going to end
the game if that happens ending the game
is in control and we scroll down and
we're gonna grab this stop all now we're
going to come up with a better thing to
do after a while but for now just to
kind of test it this is what we want to
happen so we're gonna switch to costume
crash and then the game's gonna stop now
I happen to know that there's a bug here
and the bug is is that as soon as the
game ends as soon as stop all happens
then you don't see anything else it
just resets to the beginning so I want to
actually wait for a little bit between
those two activities maybe I'll wait for
like three seconds so that way you can
see your car in its crash mode and then
you can actually know that you're crashed
so now I'm going to go in and hit play
and I'm gonna intentionally just crash
right into a wall cool and so I can see
that I've got a nice little car crash
which is fun and then my game did stop
so the only way I can play it again is
by hitting the button again and then you
can race it around your track and you
can see how how long you can make it
right and if you hit the outsides
that should make you crash as well by
the way you can also add sound effects
sound effects are fun oops hold on I did not mean to do that and so if you want
to add a sound effect that can be a fun
thing to do to add a sound effect we
have kind of tried to play with this
before you can click on the racecar here
you can go into sounds
and you can add a sound now you can add
sounds from their library you can look
around and play sounds and so what you
could what you could do is you could do
a search if you want to look for
something so if you want to add it you
click on the top icon if you just want
to play it you just hit the play button
below it right and so that's that's the
way that works so I'm going to choose to
add an explosion and what that does is
that much like costumes that makes it a
costume I can use this makes it a sound
I can use now I can use that sound
effect in my code right so what I'm
going to do is I've now got the ability
to use that sound effect I'm going to go
into the sound area and there's two
types of sounds there's play sound until
done that would be a fine one to use or
there's just play sound right now
I'm just gonna play sound explosion and
so now what you can do is you to try
your game again and now when you crash
your car you should hear a sound and see
the costume change now you probably
can't hear my sound because of I'm set
up here to record audio but it should
work for you right so you should be able
to crash your car you should be able to
hear a sound and then see the crash
alright so now we're ready to add the
final cool feature instead of just
switching to one costume which is our
crash costume and stopping the game
we're gonna play an animation animations
are really fun so here's what I want you
to do I want you to take these three
lines of code switch costume wait for
three seconds and stop all and just kind
of like set them over to the side right
so we're well actually you could delete them
because we don't really need them
anymore but I like to keep code around
because I went to all the trouble of
writing it and instead we're going to
play a crash animation now just for the
sake of practicing with functions let's
make another function called play crash
animation so go to functions create a
function play
crash animation so we're learning about
two things we're learning about
functions play crash animation the
function and we're also going to learn
about animations right so kind of kind
of a neat a little double dip so the
first thing you got to do is you're
going to go find the the start of your
function so let me get my code organized
here so you can see that functions can
be good just for kind of like describing
what's happening so I want to play this
explosion and then play a crash
animation I'm gonna do the same thing I
did last time I'm gonna call the
function first so the way you call a
function is it kind of makes a block for
you right and I put it below play sound so
it's kind of neat functions are like your
ability to make your own blocks that can
do anything right so it's really kind of
neat so now when we're touching this
color we're gonna play a sound an
explosion in this case and then we're
gonna play a crash animation alright so
how do we play an animation well the way
you play in animation we've kind of seen
the starts of an animation you switch
from one costume to the next costume and
then the same way animators do it if you
make these costumes kind of like close
together it can look like movements
happening which is kind of cool so
really any animation has to start with
the costumes so we're gonna have to go
back into our racecar again so click on
the little gear and right now I've got
two costumes I've got one called car and
one called crash here's what I want to
do instead of having one costume called
crash I want to have five so we're going
to make some copies of it so I'm going
to duplicate it now I've got two crashes
duplicate three crashes four crashes and
five crashes now you'll notice that when
you do this it picks names for you it
picked you know just crash and then
crash 1 crash 2 crash well crash 11
clash 111 not the best names I'm going
to change these names to be crash one
two three four and five oh and it's
drawing a oopsie it apparently put a
little text on there to number them I
didn't really mean to number them
all right so I want their names to be
one two three four five now I started
from the bottom to move up
I see I'm I'm currently drawing text
boxes because I've got that selected all
right I just wanted to change the names
silly computer even as you get older you
still talk to your computers quite a bit
right and so my goal is to make
eventually five copies and I want to
name them crash 1 crash 2 crash 3 crash 4
and crash 5 whoo that was harder than
I would have expected all right
so for each crash what I'm gonna do is
I'm gonna add smoke right so I'm gonna
zoom to where I can see the whole thing
because I always have to do that and I'm
gonna have some smoke coming out of my
car the first one is gonna have no smoke
the second one is gonna have small
smoke that's kind of like near the car
and then each one the smokes gonna get
bigger and farther away to draw my smoke
I'm going to draw circles I'm gonna use
some like dark gray color and I'm not an
amazing animator so I'm just gonna make
like a few circles so I'll just kind of
like make a couple circles that are kind
of like near the car to start with right
so that is the beginnings of my smoke
animation that's my crash 2 scene and by
the way you can you know you can play
these things but let's let's go and make
some more smoke so now go to the next
frame in your animation so scratch 3 or
crash 3 there's no smoke on this one
oh I do have that silly three on here that
was an accident don't do that I'll get rid of that so here's
what I want to do on frame 3 I want to
know like where were my smokes in the
last frame right and draw them a little
bigger a little higher now here's where
Tynker has a nice tool for you this tool
right up here if you click on this tool
what it'll do is it'll show you a ghost
of your previous frame so see how
whenever I click it I get a little ghost
of those old bubbles that kind of shows
me where was the last frame and that's
actually really helpful for animation
because now I want to draw them a little
bigger and a little higher right and
then you're going to keep doing this
process so there I've drawn my crash
three and now I switched to crash four now in
crash four it shows me a little ghost
and the the lady who made the virtual
pets talked about this quite a bit but
she's like you know that's how a real
animators work too right so they use
ghost to the previous frame and then
they can make them continue to get
bigger and then for my final frame there
they're gigantic right and what you can
do which is kind of fun is you can hit
this play button and then kind of see
what your animation looks like right now
we're doing a relatively simple
animation I'm just doing some smoke
circles that come off but you can do a
lot of creative things with animation
this is where like coding and art really
come together nicely you can make I mean
a hundred page animation flipbook with
with just a you know a little bit of
code and a lot of drawing if you'd like
to do that so you could spend all your
time practicing your art skills when
you're doing coding which i think is
really fun all right as soon as you've
got your crash 1 crash 2 crash 3 crash 4
and crunch 5 all set we're ready to go
write some code to actually bring your
animation to life in code so let's go
back to our code and inside of our play
crash animation we want to put a forever
loop so inside of our forever loop so
forever what we want to do is we want to
switch costumes and then wait a little
bit so let's go look at let's go
look at our commands in looks and see
if we could figure out how to do this so
one thing we could do we'll just kind of
talk about them is we could put in a next
costume and below that we could put a
time delay and that would almost work
except for our smoke would get bigger
bigger and bigger and then our car would
be cured and then our car would be
crashed and the smoke would come out
again but there would be that one frame
in there that I don't like if I used if
I just use next costume and went through
all of them there'd be that one glitch
that I don't like another thing I could
do is I could just say switch to costume
and I could just put in each one
individually and so I just have like the
first thing iss I switch to crash 1 I
wait switch crash 2 wait switch crash 3
wait and that would work it's just
tedious here's the one I want next
costume starting with so that's the
command that I actually want and I want
to start with and if you click in here
it will kind of show you your different
costumes that's nice because I'm going
to click on crash 1 but then I'm going
to take off the 1 alright and so what
it's going to do is it's going to switch
to the next costume that starts with the
word crash and so that way it won't
include our car frame in our animation
it'll just do the crash ones and you do
need a small delay between them so you
can grab a wait and you can decide how
long you want between your your
animations right so let's say that I
want point 3 seconds I don't know what's
going to look good you just have to play
with it until you figure up what looks
good and so now I'm ready to have try
my animation right so our first ever
animation together looks like my car has
disappeared so every so often there are
bugs in life and whenever you get like
weird bugs like that like my car just
disappeared where'd my car go um I'm not
quite sure what's going on there I'm
just gonna refresh the page I saved it
first should have pointed that out big
bold letters I saved it first hey
there my car's back should things like
that happen no do things like that
sometimes happen uh yeah apparently so
and your goal is just to get better with
your tools until you figure out how to
do it all right so my game is playing
just fine and now if I come around for
my big crash boom and my animation fun
and that animation is
like with the car no matter where it's
at so I kind of get this smoke that's
coming out so I'm sitting there and just
kind of like smoking I consider this a
finished game so there's all kinds of
enhancements that we can make so I'm
going to tell you about some of those
and then I'm going to go around and I'm
going to check to see how my campers did
I'll tell you what to give them just a
second to to finish theirs up I'm going
to show you some some possible
enhancements so there are some crazy
enhancements you could do to this one
one enhancement you could do is to make
a second car now you might think oh
that's gonna be a lot of trouble you
know there's no way I'm gonna take the
time to make a second car it turns out
that making a second car is actually
easier than you think
you just duplicate this car and then you
go into this other car and you change
his color like let's say I wanted him
to be blue you just have to change his
color in all your different all your
different you know versions that you've
got of your animation so I guess that's
the hard part right so I could go
through and I could I could change the
rest of them and then you change what
keys he moves on a popular set of keys
to do is WASD is kind of like your other
arrow keys and you can see that with
like just like a couple lines of code
now I can move one car with one set of
arrow keys and then the other car with
the other set of arrow keys uh actually
it didn't made my red car do that but
you can see that you can make a
two-player game pretty easily I'm gonna
undo that before I ship this but that's okay
other things you could do if you wanted
in addition to making a two-player game
you could use like speed boost so here
like my red is a slowdown and my green
is a speed-up I've also got oil slicks
that if you hit an oil slick it kind of
wipes you out so that is something that you
could add if you wanted you could also
add things like winning right so some
people don't like to make a game unless
they can win it but if you make some
color that's like a finish line you
could win your game too right so there's
a lot of neat enhancements you can make
I'm not going to go into these I was
just kind of telling you some things
you could do if you if you wanted right
and so yeah those are some some things
that you could do alright so I think
it's time to I'll tell you what before I ship my
game I'm going to delete my race car one
because I don't I don't need him that was
just demo for you guys I'm gonna save
and publish and so this is day four
connecting with Code week one I like to do
a save and publish so that other people
can see my work but I'm curious to see
to see how my campers did today
Keegan are you ready to show us your progress today your car you
all right so Dr. Keegan likes to be called Dr. K he's got a cool track
he's got an awesome blue car and then he's got a nice crash and then I saw
the smoke come off and it looks like he has a one smoker smoke animation looks fun
alright bowen did you succeed today tell us about your game oh I love your car
can you steer your car oh you bet and then what happens to your car when you hit a wall
you've got to hit a wall wooaaahhhh he crashed big time and look at your animation buddy
hey was that fun did you like coding today did you learn about
functions and animations today big day
all right McKinley are you ready to show us yours it looks like she's trying to do some of the
enhancements it looks like I see a finish line on here oh she wants to do one lap two laps kind of thing
all right crash it oh yeah
crashing animation hey McKinley you've coded a lot
but have you done animations like this before have
you done functions like this before alright so we learned a lot of good things
alright so that's all we've got for today
come back next time for the final day we're gonna do some more advanced things with
functions hopefully you all learned a lot and got some ideas to
make you game even cooler
see you next time bye
[Music]